Guide to the Livingston Family Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Herman and Emeline Hopkins Livingston Papers, 1820-1958; Series III; 7.7; (18 boxes)
  The final subseries, Cornell/Hopkins/Howland Family Papers, contains miscellaneous items created by or related to Emeline Livingston's Hopkins and Cornell ancestors and relatives. Highlights include a commonplace book filled by her grandmother Emeline Cornell, and six others created by her mother Mary Elizabeth Hopkins. Also present is a small travel diary dating from the time of the latter's April 16, 1857, marriage to Henry Hopkins; the diary has entries only at the back, which list shopping preferences and retail experiences in various European cities; it also holds receipts for items purchased during her trip.
  - Correspondence
    - Antiques, 1923-1939 (Box 8, Folder 67)
      Contains correspondence with dealers, librarians, museum curators, and others about Livingston family collections
    - Bigelow, Poultney, 1911-1932 (Box 8, Folder 68)
      Includes inscribed snapshot photograph
    - Briggs, Richard, 1923
      Related Archival Materials note
      See: Box 8, folder 67
    - Carr, Francis C., 1919-1921, undated (Box 8, Folder 69)
    - Church, Louis Palmer and Sarah (Sally) Baker Good, 1936-1937 (Box 8, Folder 70)
    - Frick Art Reference Library, 1937
    - Hopkins, Charles Vernon, 1911-1933 (Box 8, Folder 71)
    - Hopkins, Mary Elizabeth Cornell, 1881 (Box 8, Folder 72)
    - Leaming, Thomas, 1911 (Box 8, Folder 73)
    - Livingston, Anna P. (1866-1967) [sister], 1915-1932, undated (Box 8, Folder 74)
    - Livingston, Archibald R. (1868-1952) [brother], 1918 (Box 8, Folder 75)
      See also: Box 8, folder 74
    - Livingston, Edmund P. (1857-1888) [brother], 1881-1888 (Box 8, Folder 76)
    - Livingston, Edmund P. (1889-1972) [son], 1909-1917 (Box 8, Folder 77-79)
    - Livingston, Edmund P. (1889-1972) [son], 1918-1937 (Box 9, Folder 80-85)
      Includes one folder of letters to Edmund Livingston from third-party correspondents, and World War I material
    - Livingston, Henry (Brud) H. (1887-1960) [son] and Mary Eleanor, 1908-1926, undated (Box 9, Folder 86)
    - Livingston, Herman (1856-1936), 1917 (Box 9, Folder 87)
    - Livingston, Herman Jr. (1883-1951) [son] and Olga, 1897-1958 (Box 9, Folder 88)
    - Livingston, Herman T. (1827-1899) [father], 1881-1899 (Box 9, Folder 89)
      Includes a letter to grandson Edmund
    - Livingston, John C. (1862-1956) [brother], 1884 (Box 9, Folder 90)
    - McAlpin, George Lodowick, 1911-1916 (Box 9, Folder 91)
    - McClelland, Nancy, 1939
    - Museum of the City of New York, 1937-1938
    - Rogers & Webb
      - Correspondence, 1914-1928 (Box 10, Folder 92-94)
      - Invoices, 1916-1921 (Box 10, Folder 95)
      - Statements (vessel reports), 1914-1932 (Box 10, Folder 96-97)
    - Rogers, Anne Coleman, 1880-1907, undated (Box 10, Folder 98)
    - Stow, Millicent, 1939
    - Whittlesey, Charles White, 1919, 1921, undated (Box 10, Folder 99)
    - Williams, Sarah (Sallie) Livingston (1871-1959) [sister], 1915-1929, undated (Box 11, Folder 100)
    - General correspondence, 1889-1936, undated (Box 11, Folder 101-102)
    - Invitations, 1882-1919 (Box 11, Folder 103)
      Includes the Livingstons' wedding (1882) and events at the White House (President William Howard Taft), among others
    - Condolence letters, cards, and telegrams, to Emeline Livingston and family, 1936-1938 (Box 11, Folder 104-107)
    - Condolence letters, cards, and telegrams, to Emeline Livingston and family, 1936-1938 (Box 12, Folder 108-112)
  - Personal papers
    - Estate of Herman T. Livingston [father], 1899-1900 (Box 12, Folder 113)
    - [Folder number not used] (Box 12, Folder 114)
    - Livingston, Edmund P. (1889-1972) [son]: childhood writings and First Communion book, 1904, undated (Box 12, Folder 115)
    - Livingston, Emeline C.
      - Confirmation book, bank book, recipe, cancelled check, 1920-1938, undated (Box 12, Folder 116)
      - Diaries, 1937-1940 (Box 12, Folder 117)
      - Greene County Historical Society membership certificate, 1929
      - Hopkins family genealogical notes, 1951, undated (Box 12, Folder 118)
      - Postcards, undated (Box 12, Folder 119)
      - Scrapbook, with loose newspaper clippings, post cards, invitations, 1878-1920s (Box 13, Folder 120-122)
        Includes invitations to dances at Yale College, 1878-1880
      - Scrapbook, with loose newspaper clippings, 1918-1935 (Box 14, Folder 123-124)
      - Local history publications, 1925-1940 (Box 14, Folder 125)
    - Livingston, Herman
      - Diaries, 1887-1892 (Box 14, Folder 126-127)
      - Diaries, 1893-1907 (Box 15, Folder 128-132)
      - Diaries, 1908-1922 (Box 16, Folder 133-137)
      - Diaries, 1923-1935 (Box 17, Folder 138-142)
      - Diary, 1936 (Box 18, Folder 143)
      - Maritime photos, 1920s (Box 18, Folder 144)
      - Will and obituaries, 1935-1937 (Box 18, Folder 145)
      - Yale University, 1899 (Box 18, Folder 146)
      - Miscellaneous documents and letters, 1870-1921 (Box 18, Folder 147)
        Includes delegate's badge for 1900 Republication National Convention, and papers regarding the Amorilla
    - Livingston, Herman and Emeline C.
      - Bank check registers, 1911-1923 (Box 18, Folder 148-151)
      - Bank check registers, 1924-1934 (Box 19, Folder 152-156)
      - Bank statements, 1924-1932 (Box 20, Folder 157-161)
      - Bank statements, 1932-1935 (Box 21, Folder 162-167)
      - Bank statements, 1935-1936 (Box 22, Folder 168-169)
      - Bank statements, 1931-1936 (Box 22, Folder 170)
      - Income tax documents, 1919-1934 (Box 23, Folder 171-177)
      - Investment receipts and records (including Hopkins and Cornell estates), 1897-1935
      - Investment records, 1910-1939 (Box 23, Folder 178-181)
      - Lewis F. Payn Oil Company investment records, 1908-1919 (Box 24, Folder 182-183)
      - Oak Hill expense ledger, 1906-1915 (Box 24, Folder 184)
      - Miscellaneous documents, ephemera, clippings, etc., 1886-1934 (Box 24, Folder 185)
        Includes land survey (1886), newspaper article on Oak Hill (1934), and Leslie's Weekly (Oct. 21, 1899)
  - Photographs and prints
    - Hoon, Chang Yen: portrait, circa 1897 (Box 24, Folder 186)
    - Lewis F. Payn Oil Company: oil derrick, circa 1910
    - Livingston, Herman and Emeline C.: portrait photographs of couple and children, 1877-1904, undated (Box 24, Folder 187-189)
    - Livingston, Edmund P. (1889-1972) [son]: snapshot album, photographs of Yale friends and Oak Hill, 1908-1911 (Box 24, Folder 190)
    - Oak Hill snapshots, undated (Box 25, Folder 191)
    - Pruyn, J. V. L. and Anna Fenn: library of home at 13 Elk Street, Albany, NY, 1909 Nov
    - Ships
      - Hudson-Fulton celebration, 1909 Oct 6 (Box 25, Folder 192)
      - Schooner Amorilla [owned by Livingston], 1926, undated (Box 25, Folder 193)
      - Nielsen, August: Sloop Rascal, undated
      - Rosenfeld, Morris: Schooner Teragram, undated
      - Rudder "Nautotypes", circa 1903
      - Stebbins, N. L.: unidentified ships, undated
      - Miscellaneous photographs, prints, and clippings, undated (Box 25, Folder 194)
      - Miscellaneous photographs and prints, undated
    - Yale College Class of 1879: crew and reunion group portraits, 1879-1929
  - Cornell/Hopkins/Howland family papers
    - Cornell, Emeline Howland
      - Commonplace book with practice writings, circa 1820 (Box 25, Folder 195)
      - New-Bedford Daily Mercury, vol. 1, no. 137, with notice of marriage (p. 3), 1831 Nov 8
    - Hopkins, Charles Vernon
      - Alien registration, will, memorial, 1920-1935 (Box 25, Folder 196)
      - Diploma, St. Paul's School, 1887
      - Estate papers, 1935-1936 (Box 25, Folder 197)
      - Postcards and ephemera, undated (Box 25, Folder 198)
    - Hopkins, Henry: correspondence, 1849-1876 (Box 25, Folder 199)
    - Hopkins, Mary Elizabeth Cornell
      - Commonplace books, with poetry, essays, etc., 1845-1848 (Box 25, Folder 200-202)
      - Commonplace books, with copied poetry, essays, etc., 1851-1868 (Box 26, Folder 203-205)
      - Dreka's dictionary blotter [word-book with blotting-case], 1886 (Box 26, Folder 206)
      - Travel diary [Henry Penny's Patent Improved Metallic Books], listing shops and tradesmen visited in Europe, with trade cards and invoices for purchases, 1857 (Box 26, Folder 207)
    - Hopkins and Cornell family portrait photographs, 1877, undated (Box 26, Folder 208)
    - Howland, Sarah Francis: will, 1916-1918 (Box 26, Folder 209)
    - Recipe book, with Hopkins and New Bedford entries; loose manuscript recipes also in folder, circa 1850-1890s (Box 26, Folder 210)
    - Willis/Cornell genealogy, undated (Box 26, Folder 211)
    - Miscellaneous, 1891, undated (Box 26, Folder 212)
      Includes booklet "The Catskill of 'The Yesterdays'"
- Anna P. Livingston Papers, 1853-1968; Series IV; 4; (10 boxes) + 1 broadside folder
  Series IV is organized into three subseries: Correspondence, Personal Papers, and Photographs.
  Anna Pendleton Livingston (1866–1967)
  Anna Pendleton Livingston was the eldest daughter of Herman T. Livingston (1827-1899) and Susan Rogers Livingston (1835-1911). Born on January 6, 1866, she was an adventurer with a fondness for animals, and traveled widely, visiting Bermuda, Cuba, Japan, the Philippines, Hawaii, Mexico, and Panama, between the late nineteenth century and the 1950s. She moved with her younger brother Archibald R. Livingston (1868-1952), an engineer and a career Army officer, to Canon City, Colorado, and La Jolla, California, before they both settled in the countryside west of Medford, Oregon, in 1925; she remained there until her death at age 101, on July 19, 1967, and is buried in the Livingston family vault at Linlithgo, New York.
  During the last years of World War I, Anna Livingston served as a "marraine de guerre" for a American, Belgian, and British soldiers, as well as one French girl. The "war godmother" program promoted correspondence between civilian women and enlisted men in order to provide comfort through the hardships of war, particularly important for Belgians who had very limited contact with family members then living under German occupation.
  Anna Pendleton Livingston's papers contain a selection of letters she received over her lifetime, but are concentrated within the first quarter of the twentieth century, particularly the World War I period. Notable are those sent to her during the war by her brother Archibald, a major in the United States Army's 115th Engineers Expeditionary Force active in the European theater, and by Clyde Vincent Simpson (1898-1947), an officer in Troop H of the 12th Calvary. Anna Livingston met Simpson while he was stationed in Canon City, Colorado, and their relationship continued throughout his thirty-five-year international career with the United States Army. Simpson married Lois Boudinot Keith in 1920; the correspondence files document that union through letters, telegrams, photographs, and pressed flowers. The "marraine de guerre" letters, postcards, and photographs that Livingston received are filed together as a group within the Correspondence subseries; they carry messages of gratitude for her support and her parcels of goods, as well as expressions of friendship toward America and the American soldiers.
  Also notable for their international content are thirteen folders holding letters Livingston received from two friends, Elizabeth H. Smith (writing from India and England, 1912-1919), and an otherwise unidentified "C.H.H." (writing from Japan, 1902-1905). The latter file holds an inscribed photograph of "Catherine" placed there during processing because her handwriting matches that in the letters.
  Personal Papers primarily contains ephemera and three address books, but also a diary of a camping trip that Anna Livingston took with two female friends through Chaffee County, Colorado, between July 24 and August 17, 1903. Sites mentioned included Salida, Poncha Park, the Taylor and Gunnison rivers, Cottonwood Pass, Monarch Pass, and the Collegiate Peaks; the last pages list the flowers she recognized and a financial accounting of the trip. A photograph album documenting the trip is filed in the following subseries. Also present are three documents signed by Filipino president Emilio Aguinaldo (1869-1964), which Anna received as a gift in 1900.
  The Photographs subseries contains a mix of images: portraits and landscapes, loose photographs and bound photograph albums, postcards and half-tones, and identified and unidentified subjects. Among the earliest is an album of photographs from a childhood summer at the family's home in Newport, Rhode Island. Perhaps most remarkable are the two albums holding snapshots and purchased commercial images from Livingston's trips to Bermuda (1888 and 1894), Mexico (1895), and Nassau (1897), and her trip with Margaret Aldrich to Hawaii, the Philippines, and Japan (1900). There are also albums containing snapshots of labeled and unidentified images of the American West, often featuring Livingston on horseback, and one which may be images of Casper, Wyoming. Anna and Archibald Livingston were both photographers, often traveled together, and compiled photograph albums; but for their bookplates or handwritten captions, their albums are very similar. Readers should consult both siblings' series when looking for early twentieth-century images of the American West and Southwest.
  - Correspondence
    Includes photographs when enclosed with letters
    - Barber, Harriet Bayard Townsend, 1914-1935 (Box 27, Folder 213)
      Includes photograph of Herman Livingston home, Newport, Rhode Island
    - Beall, Wellwood and family, 1944-1957 (Box 27, Folder 214)
    - Blue Cross Fund, 1917 (Box 27, Folder 215)
    - Brewster, Dorothy Williams [niece], 1966-1967 (Box 27, Folder 216)
    - Dagwell, Benjamin D., 1961 (Box 27, Folder 217)
    - H., C. H. [letters signed "C.H.H." or "K"], 1898-1905 (Box 27, Folder 218)
    - Hooper family, 1914-1967 (Box 27, Folder 219)
    - Kobayash, Yasuji, undated (Box 27, Folder 220)
    - Lindenberger, Edith, 1967, undated (Box 27, Folder 221)
    - Livingston, Alida Schuyler
      See: Box 28, folder 228
    - Livingston, Archibald R. (1868-1952) [brother], 1916-1919 (Box 27, Folder 222-223)
      See also: Box 28, folder 229
    - Livingston, Edmund P. (1889-1972) [nephew], 1916-1919 (Box 27, Folder 224)
      Includes one letter from Herman Livingston to Edmund, forwarded to Anna
    - Livingston, Emeline Cornell, 1908-1909 (Box 27, Folder 225)
    - Livingston, Henry H. (1887-1960) [nephew] and Mary Eleanor Curran, 1937-1965, undated (Box 27, Folder 226)
    - Livingston, Henry H. (1918-2008) [great-nephew] and Maria Burroughs, 1945-1966, undated (Box 27, Folder 227)
    - Livingston, Herman (1883-1951) [nephew] and Olga Kobbé, 1931-1967, undated (Box 28, Folder 228)
      See also: Box 27, folder 224
    - Livingston, John C. (1862-1956) [brother], 1918-1919 (Box 28, Folder 229)
      Contains two letters from Archibald Livingston to John, forwarded to Anna
    - Livingston, Louise Alida (1893-1967) [niece], 1951-1965, undated (Box 28, Folder 230-231)
    - Livingston family members, miscellaneous, 1939-1967 (Box 28, Folder 232)
    - "Marraine de guerre" correspondence
      - Allegaert, Renaat [René], 1917-1920 (Box 28, Folder 233)
      - Anson, Alfred, 1917 Sep 29 (Box 28, Folder 234)
      - DeLeuze, René, 1916-1918 (Box 28, Folder 235)
      - Gohy, Victor, 1918 (Box 28, Folder 236)
      - Manzana, Marie-Thérèse and Marguerite, 1917-1924 (Box 28, Folder 237)
      - Rullaert, René, 1918-1919 (Box 28, Folder 238)
      - Schuermeans, Jos, undated (Box 28, Folder 239)
      - T'Sjoen, Charles, 1917-1918 (Box 28, Folder 240)
      - Vander Borght, George, 1917-1918 (Box 28, Folder 241)
        See also: Box 28, folder 238
    - Primrose, Margaret, 1948-1949, undated (Box 29, Folder 242)
    - Rice, Harriet Langdon Pruyn, 1935-1938 (Box 29, Folder 243)
    - Simpson, Clyde Vincent and Lois Keith
      - Correspondence, 1915-1919 (Box 29, Folder 244-252)
      - Correspondence, 1919-1946, undated (Box 30, Folder 253-256)
      - Photographs, undated (Box 30, Folder 257-258)
    - Smith, Elizabeth H., 1912-1915 (Box 30, Folder 259-260)
      Includes material about Patty Aberigh-Mackay, a British painter working in India.
    - Smith, Elizabeth H., 1915-1917 (Box 31, Folder 261-268)
    - Smith, Elizabeth H., 1918-1919, undated (Box 32, Folder 269-270)
    - Southern Oregon Historical Society, 1951 May (Box 32, Folder 271)
    - Tanaka, Yuho, Yukey R., and Teruko, 1909-1917 (Box 32, Folder 272)
    - United States, Army, Cavalry Regiment, 12th., Troops H and E, 1914-1916 (Box 32, Folder 273)
    - Van Keuren, Floyd and Helen, 1918-1919, undated (Box 32, Folder 274)
    - Wells, J.S.C., 1916-1917 (Box 32, Folder 275)
    - Williams, Sarah (Sallie) Livingston (1871-1959) [sister] and George, 1916-1940 (Box 32, Folder 276)
    - Wood, Edith, 1933, undated (Box 32, Folder 277)
    - Unidentified British soldier (signed "Jaw"), 1916 (Box 32, Folder 278)
    - General correspondence, personal, 1910-1967 (Box 32, Folder 279-280)
    - General correspondence, business, 1920-1962 (Box 32, Folder 281)
  - Personal papers
    - Address books (3), undated (Box 33, Folder 282)
    - "The Adventures of Anne", 1915 (Box 33, Folder 283)
      Scrapbook-format compilation of humorous poems written by APL's friends about her trip to Panama
    - Aguinaldo, Emilio, autographed documents, 1898-1900 (Box 33, Folder 284)
    - Bible (London, undated), 1903 (Box 33, Folder 285)
    - Calendar, 1906
    - Colorado Mountain Club: Trail and Timberline, 1915-1916
    - Diary of Colorado camping trip, 1903 (Box 33, Folder 286)
      See also: Box 34, folder 293
    - Ephemera, miscellaneous, 1923-1968, undated (Box 33, Folder 287)
      Includes obituaries and newspaper article about sale of Medford/Jacksonville house
    - French print [view of Quimper], circa 1934
    - Japanese books (2), circa 1890
    - Japanese paintings (on silk and on paper), circa 1890
    - Japanese polychrome woodblock prints (14), circa 1890
    - Travel literature: American West and Southwest, 1909-1964, undated (Box 33, Folder 288-289)
      Includes material on Glacier, Yellowstone, and Mesa Verde national parks, Grand Canyon, Phoenix, and the Colorado Mountain Club; railroad schedules (1912-1913); Pacific Mail Steamship ephemera (1923)
    - Wedding dress fabric [fragments] worn by Susan Rogers Livingston, 1853 (Box 34, Folder 290)
    - World War I ephemera and broadsides, 1916-1919 (Box 34, Folder 291)
      Includes a form letter from King George V, an issue of "The Whizz-Bang" (February 1916), a "Kamp Kearny Kalendar," newspaper clippings, and other items
    - World War I posters (9), 1918, undated
      Posters produced for the YMCA-YWCA United War Work Campaign and the United States Shipping Board; artists include James Montgomery Flagg, W. B. King, Albert Herter, and Adolph Treidler.
  - Photographs
    - Album: Rhode Island, Newport, circa 1880 (Box 34, Folder 292)
    - Album: Bermuda, Mexico, and Nassau, 1888-1897
    - Album: Colorado, California, Quebec, and South Carolina, 1897-1901
      Includes commercial and personal photographs of train trip from Colorado to California (1897-1898); Central Pacific Railroad (1897); Quebec, Canada (1901); Aiken, South Carolina (1901); and a houseboat trip from New Berne, North Carolina, to Hackensack, New Jersey (1901); ephemera includes guidebooks to Quebec (1900-1901); invitation aboard Sheffield Phelps's houseboat Nirodha
    - Album: Hawaii, the Philippines, and Japan, 1900
    - Album: American West and Southwest, 1902-1905 (Box 34, Folder 293)
      Snapshots include Colorado camping trip (1903); Grand Canyon and Petrified Forest, Arizona (1903); Acoma pueblo (1903); Yellowstone (1904). Livingston's diary of the camping trip is in Box 33, folder 286.
    - Album: American West and Southwest, 1905-1908
      Snapshots include scenes in Routt County, Wetmore, and Wagon Wheel Gap, Colorado (1907-1908), and in California: Mariposa Grove, Truckee River, Lundy, Lake Tahoe, and Yosemite (1905)
    - Album: Wyoming, Casper [?], circa 1918 (Box 35, Folder 294)
    - Album: American West and Southwest, circa 1920 (Box 35, Folder 295-296)
      Includes several photographs mesas, camping trip, and natural stone arch [(Rainbow Bridge?; negatives of latter in Box 162]
    - California, circa 1910, undated (Box 35, Folder 297)
    - Colorado, undated (Box 35, Folder 298)
      Includes images of a cattle drive
    - France, undated (Box 35, Folder 299)
    - Historic houses and buildings, circa 1880-circa 1959 (Box 36, Folder 300-301)
      Includes photographs, postcards, and clippings of famous and vernacular buildings in Connecticut, upstate New York, Massachusetts, Pennsylvania, and Virginia; one folder of photographs of Sag Harbor, New York; similar material is filed Box 40, folders 343-344.
    - Japan and Hong Kong, circa 1900 (Box 36, Folder 302)
    - Livingston, Anna Pendleton
      - Formal portraits, undated (Box 36, Folder 303)
        See also Archibald Livingston's scrapbook, Box 134
      - Snapshots with friends, 1917-1966, undated (Box 36, Folder 304)
      - Travel photos, miscellaneous, 1914-1915, undated (Box 36, Folder 305)
    - Rogers family, 1911, 1914 (Box 36, Folder 306)
      Includes set of images from the wedding of Anne P. Rogers to J. Griswold Webb (1914)
    - Oregon, Medford/Jacksonville, 1938-1967, undated (Box 36, Folder 307)
    - People, miscellaneous, 1884, undated (Box 36, Folder 308-309)
      Includes portrait of Geronimo by A. Frank Randall
    - Pets, undated (Box 36, Folder 310)
    - Places, unidentified [most are the American West], undated (Box 36, Folder 311)
- Archibald R. Livingston Papers, 1880-1951; Series V; 3; (7 boxes) + 1 broadside folder
  Series V is organized into three subseries: Personal Papers, Military Service Papers, and Photographs and Prints.
  Archibald R. Livingston (1868–1952)
  Archibald Rogers Livingston was the son of Herman T. Livingston (1827-1899) and Susan Rogers Livingston (1835-1911). Born in New York City on November 23, 1868, he was educated at St. Paul's School (Class of 1886) and graduated from the civil engineering program at the Columbia University School of Mines in 1891. Livingston's military career began with his enlistment in Company A of the 13th Regiment, 3rd Brigade, National Guard of Pennsylvania, where he was stationed in Homestead, Montrose, and Gettysburg (1892-1895). He served with the 1st Regiment of United States Volunteer Engineers during the Spanish-American War (1898-1899); his unit worked in Puerto Rico to repair infrastructure damaged by Spanish soldiers. In 1901 Livingston became a superintendent with the Empire Zinc Company of Canon City, Colorado, and joined the Colorado National Guard; while with the company he was called to serve along the Mexican border and at Palomas, Mexico, on Pershing's "Punitive Expedition" in pursuit of Pancho Villa. When the United States declared war on Germany in 1917, Livingston was a captain with the 157th Infantry. He transferred to the 115th Engineers Corps in September 1917 and was promoted to major a month afterward. Composed almost entirely of Colorado men, the 115th was first stationed at Camp Kearny, near La Jolla, California, and then in France and Germany from July 1918 through July 1919.